Finding Aid for Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library
Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy (University of Michigan) records
1917-2013
1950-2002
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy.
87209 Bimu C448 2
17 linear feet (in 18 boxes)
10.2 GB
The Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy (formerly the School of Public Policy) developed out of various institutes at the University of Michigan including the Institute of Social and Public Administration the Institute of Public Administration, and the Institute of Public Policy Studies. The School provides courses and conducts research in areas of public administration and public policy issues. Records include administrative files, correspondence, topical files and some material on research projects.
The records were transferred by the Institute of Public Policy Studies in 1972 (donor no. 2951 ); additional materials were transferred from the School of Public Policy in 1997, and from the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy in 2006
The Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Box 17
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 15, 17-18 and online
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files, are restricted for thirty (30) years from the date of their creation.
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
In 1914, the Department of Political Science established a graduate program which led to a master's degree in municipal administration. Courses were taken from the curricula of various departments, schools and colleges including Economics, Landscape Design, the Law School, and the College of Engineering. By the mid-1930s, a demand had developed for individuals trained to perform various administrative functions in Michigan. In 1936, the Institute of Social and Public Administration was established as part of the graduate school at the university to address this need. A program was developed to satisfy demands for trained administrators who could work in the fields of public administration, land utilization, and social work. In 1938, the Bureau of Government, a center for research on municipal administration, became part of the University Institute of Public and Social Administration.
The Regents of the University of Michigan approved a plan for the establishment of the Institute of Public Administration (IPA) on September 28, 1945. A formal announcement of the formation of the new institute was issued in March 1946. The new program had several goals. They included training students in the field of public administration as well as conducting research on matters of public interest such as taxes, employment, etc. Offering services to public officials and legislative bodies was also identified as one of the goals of the program. Finally, the program would cooperate with government offices to offer "in-service training" to advanced students, as well as to offer short courses to public employees. Instruction and research in the fields of law, engineering, public health, and economics, among others, were integrated into the program.
In 1949, the IPA participated in the first of a series of international programs about public policy and administration issues. The IPA was one of six American universities to host Germans who were instructed in American social/political institutions and democratic skills, as well as other subjects. The second international project in which the Institute of Public Administration was involved in the1950s was the establishment of the Institute of Public Administration at the University of the Philippines in 1952. The goal of this project was to train Filipinos for work in public administration and help Philippine government employees improve their effectiveness. The Institute was staffed by professors from the University of Michigan, although over time they were replaced by instructors from the Philippine University. During the 1960s, the Institute worked on another international project entitled the Taiwan Center for Public and Business Administration. The Taiwan Center was a joint effort by the government of the Republic of China, the University of Michigan, and the Agency for International Aid. The Center offered an undergraduate degree in public and business administration, as well as an in-service training program. In addition to the in-service and undergraduate degree programs, the Taiwan Center also developed the Chinese Journal of Administration, held seminars for Taiwan's government officials, and sent faculty from Taiwan to the United States for advanced training.
In 1968, the Institute of Public Policy Studies (IPPS) was formed. The new program synthesized the offerings of the Institute of Public Administration with courses in economic analysis, quantitative methods, and other subjects. It was one of the first graduate programs in public policy in the United States. The program at the University of Michigan was modeled on an interdisciplinary approach to public policy issues that used the techniques and tools of the social sciences to address social problems. Links with the schools of Law, Business, Natural Resources, and Public Health allowed the program to expand the areas of expertise that were offered. The mission of IPPS was to research public policy issues and train students for careers in public services. It also recognized the absence of a program in which public officials could enhance and renew their skills. A series of policy seminars for public officials was established to address this need. Over the time of its existence, IPPS also played a leading role in the development of an international curriculum in public policy studies.
In 1995, IPPS was established as an independent school within the University of Michigan and was subsequently designated as the School of Public Policy.
In 1999, the School of Public Policy was re-named the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy in honor of the 38th President of the United States, Gerald R. Ford, who graduated from the University of Michigan in 1935. Since 2001, the school has offered joint doctoral programs with the departments of economics, political science, and sociology. The school began construction of a new home, Joan and Sanford Weil Hall, in the fall of 2004 and dedicated the building in the fall of 2006.
Directors of the Institute of Public Policy Studies
1950-1960 John W. Lederle
1960-1967 Ferrel Heady
1968-1973 John Patrick Crecine
1973-1974 Thomas J. Anton (Acting Director)
1974-1979 Jack L. Walker
1979-1983 Edward M. Gramlich
1983-1987 Paul N. Courant
1987-1989 Edie N. Goldenberg
1989-1990 Paul N. Courant
1991-1995 Edward M. Gramlich
Deans of the School of Public Policy
1995-1997 Edward M. Gramlich
1997-1999 John Chamberlain (Interim)
1999- Rebecca M. Blank
Deans of the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy
1999- 2007 Rebecca M. Blank
2007-2017 Susan M. Collins
2017- Michael S. Barr
The University of Michigan Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy record group documents the history and development of public policy studies at the University of Michigan. The records contain some information on the beginning of instruction in public administration in 1915 and the formation of the Institute of Social and Public Administration in 1936. The bulk of the material documents the administration and subsequent reorganizations of the academic unit currently known as the School of Public Policy. Records include correspondence, minutes, historical materials and topical files concerning the Institute, its Lansing Office, its programs in the Republic of China and documented the Philippine Islands, and the Michigan Constitutional Convention of 1961- 1962. the records have been received in three major accessions, 1972 (boxed 1-9), 1997 (boxes 10-14) and 2006 (boxes 15-18).
Most of the materials comprising the 1972 accession cover the period from the 1950s to the mid-1980s. Unfortunately, few documents about the establishment and development of the public policy studies curriculum between 1915 and 1945 exist. Particular strengths of the record group are the materials on the Philippine Institute of Public Administration and the Taiwan Center for Public and Business Administration Education. The German Training Program files also offer insight into international interests of the public administration faculty at the University of Michigan. The German Training Program was a program established to provide Germans with a knowledge of American political and social institutions, democratic skills, and development of individual competence in fields of knowledge such as journalism, pedagogy, and public administration. Other series in the School of Public Policy records allow for a general overview of the structure of the School of Public Policy. They also demonstrate the composition and research interests of the faculty and students in the department.
The records comprising the 1997 accession from the School of Public Policy were primarily arranged chronologically. This arrangement has been retained and the record group has been broken down into a Chronological Files series, several Topical Files series, a Sound Recordings Series, and a Photographs series. It should be noted that some of the files in the Topical Files series include documents created after the dates noted in the series heading.
The 2006 accession consisted of additional administrative files and material relating to the dedication of the Joan and Sanford Weil Hall groundbreaking and dedication.
China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Public administration.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Public administration.; Gramlich, Edward M.; Heady, Ferrel.; Lederle, John William, 1912-; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Administration.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Policy Studies.; University of Michigan. School of Public Policy.; University of Michigan. Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy.; Magsaysay, Ramon, 1907-1957.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Administration.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Policy Studies.; University of the Philippines.; University of Michigan. Institute of Public Policy Studies.
- John W. Lederle, 1952-1960
  The John W. Lederle series (.5 linear feet) primarily contains correspondence to and from John W. Lederle during his tenure as director of the Institute of Public Administration. It covers the period between 1952 and 1960. Lederle's correspondence includes both general information about the day-to-day management of the Institute, as well as information specific to the development of the Institute. Lederle corresponded with individuals involved in creating/developing public policy programs at other institutions around the country. These letters partially illustrate the development of this area of study at various universities.
  - Correspondence, 1952-1960
    - 1952-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1960 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
- Robert H. Pealy, 1954-1963
  Robert H. Pealy was a research associate and the editor of publications at the IPA for several years. The documents in the Robert H. Pealy series (.5 linear feet) consist of correspondence to and from Pealy regarding his activities at the Institute. The series spans the years from 1954 to 1963.
  - Correspondence
    - Regarding Consultation, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963 (Box 1)
- Ferrel Heady, 1956-1967
  The Ferrel Heady series (1.5 linear feet) is comprised of correspondence and miscellaneous documents created between 1956 and 1967. Heady acted as director of the Institute of Public Administration between 1960 and 1967. The correspondence is primarily concerned with the daily activities of the Institute, however, it also includes items about the research which Heady conducted during this time. The Miscellaneous subseries includes papers sent to Heady for suggestions or review.
  - Correspondence, 1956-1959; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1966; 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1967; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Administrative Files, 1917-1968
  The Administrative Files, 1917-1968 series (1 linear feet) contains materials documenting the history of the public policies curriculum between 1917 and 2002. This includes minutes of the Executive Committee of the Institute of Public and Social Administration meetings. Minutes of other meetings are available for the Political Science Executive Committee and meetings of the Research Assistants. The Historical subseries contains several historical essays. Documents in each of these subseries offer insight into the development of the Institute. The Lansing Office subseries contains documents about the Institute of Public Administration's Lansing office which served as a center for faculty and students involved in state government and administration projects. The office existed between 1957 and 1968. Finally, the Report of the Institute for Public Research subseries contains the 1917 report which was delivered to the Regents of the University of Michigan recommending the creation of a center dedicated to training individuals in public administration.
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1934-1968; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Political Science Department Executive Committee Minutes, 1942-1946 (Box 3)
  - Lansing Office, 1956-1967 (Box 3)
  - Budgets, 1933-1951; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Minutes of Meetings of Research Assistants, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
  - Director's Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
  - Report of the Institute for Public Research, 1917 (Box 3)
  - Alumni of the Curriculum in Municipal Administration (Box 3)
  - Historical Materials, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - News Clippings, 1936-1960 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Questionnaires, 1954 (Box 3)
- Administrative Files, 1968-2013
  The Administrative Files, 1968-2013 series (3 linear feet and digital files) contains materials documenting the history of the public policies curriculum between 1970 and 2002. The Alumni Society Board of Governors materials include minutes of the board's biannual meetings for the period between 1990 and 2002 as well as material documenting the election of board members between the years 1999 and 2002. Budget materials include reference material, correspondence and material supporting the annual budget conferences for the years 1992 through 1994. The Executive Committee records contain correspondence, minutes, and agendas documenting the committee's activities from the year 1968 through 1997. The Faculty Committee records include correspondence and minutes documenting their regular meetings for the years 1996 and 1997. The institute of Public Policy Studies Review materials document an internal review that was conducted in the year 1979. The Memoranda of Agreement documents include records supporting collaborative agreements and cost sharing between the School of Public Policy and various departments across campus. The series also includes are materials of faculty retreats.
  - Alumni Society Board of Governors
    - Elections
      - 1999-2002, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - General
      - Mailing, 1991 (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 15)
      - Retiring Member's Letters (Box 15)
        [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2033 ]
    - Meetings
      - 1990
        - June, 2 folders (Box 15)
        - November, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - 1991
        - April, 2 folders (Box 15)
        - October (Box 15)
      - 1992
        - April (Box 15)
        - October (Box 15)
      - 1993
        - April (Box 15)
        - October (Box 15)
      - 1994
        - April (Box 15)
        - September (Box 15)
      - 1995
        - April (Box 15)
        - October, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - 1996
        - March (Box 15)
        - September (Box 15)
      - 1997
        - March (Box 16)
        - September (Box 16)
      - 1998
        - March (Box 16)
        - October, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - 2000
        - September, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - 2001
        - March (Box 16)
      - 2002
  - Budget
    - Conference
      - 1992-1993 (Box 16)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence
      - 1992-1993 (Box 16)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 16)
    - General
      - 1991-1992, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Special Transfers, 1993-1994 (Box 16)
  - Executive Committee
    - Correspondence
      - Elections
        - 1995-1997 (Box 17)
          [Personnel records restricted until July 01, 2027 ]
      - General
        - 1976-1977 (Box 17)
        - 1977-1978 (Box 17)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 17)
        - 1985-1986 (Box 17)
        - 1987-1988 (Box 17)
        - 1995-1997 (Box 17)
    - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Resources
      - 1968-1975, 9 folders (Box 17)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 17)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 17)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 17)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 17)
      - 1982-1989 (Box 17)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 17)
      - 2007-2008
        [Restricted until July 01, 2042 ]
      - 2008-2009
      - 2009-2010
      - 2010-2011
      - 2011-2012
      - 2012-2013
        [Restricted until July 01, 2043 ]
  - Faculty Committee
    - Correspondence, 1996-1997; undated (Box 17)
    - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Resources, 1996-1997 (Box 17)
    - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Resources, 2011-2012
      [Restricted until July 01, 2032 ]
    - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Resources, 2008-2009
    - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Resources, 2009-2010
    - Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Resources, 2010-2011
  - Institute of Public Policy Studies Review
    - General, 1979 (Box 17)
    - Information sheets on Student Internships, undated (Box 17)
    - Student Rosters, 1969-1978 (Box 17)
    - Syllabi, 1978-1979 (Box 17)
  - Memoranda of Agreement, 1970-1995 (Box 17)
  - Strategic Plan, Draft, 1989 (Box 17)
  - Faculty Retreats, 2008
    [Restricted until July 1, 2032 ]
  - Faculty Retreats, 2009
  - Faculty Retreats, 2010
  - Faculty Retreats, 2011
  - Faculty Retreats, 2012
- Conference Files, 1947-1970
  The Conference Files series (.5 linear feet) includes information pertaining to conferences on public administration issues organized between 1947 and 1970. Comprised of documents about conferences and short courses, this series provides evidence of the vitality and commitment of the department's members to continuing education and pursuit of the questions facing individuals in the field of public administration.
  - Management Clinic for City Managers, 1949-1959 (Box 3)
  - Annual Short Course for Assessing Officers, 1947-1970; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Upper Peninsula Conference for Tax Assessing Officers, 1954-1965 (Box 3)
  - Institute for Mayors and Councilmen, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
  - Municipal Purchasing Conference, 1951-1967 (Box 4)
  - Municipal Finance Officers Training Institute, 1951-1968 (Box 4)
- Public Policy Organizations, 1946-1968
  The Public Policy Organizations series (0.5 linear feet) includes information primarily pertaining to national and international public policy organizations. Documents in this series illustrate activities which members of the public policy faculty at the University of Michigan performed for various conferences and organizations in the 1940s and 1950s. These files offer an overview of the issues facing individuals involved in public administration during this period.
  - Midwest Management Conference, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - American Society for Public Administration, 1949-195- (Box 4)
  - Advisory Committee of the Bureau of Appointments and Occupational Information, 1946-1949 (Box 4)
  - National Institute of Public Affairs, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Conference of Political Scientists, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
  - International City Managers' Association, 1959-1964 (Box 4)
  - Board Control of Student Publications, 1947-1950 (Box 4)
  - Study of Washtenaw County Government, undated (Box 4)
- German Training File, 1950-1952
  In 1949, the University of Michigan was one of six American universities to participate in the Political and Social Science Training Program. The program was offered to a group of Germans and is described in the series entitled the German Training File (.5 linear feet). This series is comprised of documents describing the purpose of the program and the University of Michigan's involvement in it. Of particular interest are evaluation forms from individuals who participated in the program. They indicate participants' reactions to the program, to the United States, and to the value of the program.
  - Reports and Fund Requests, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Diagnostic Council Minutes, 1950 (Box 4)
  - State Department Reports, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Contract Requests for Appointment, 1951 (Box 4)
  - German Program-Second Semester, 1951 (Box 4)
  - State Department Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 4)
  - Evaluation Interviews, 1951 (Box 4)
  - German Government Training Project, 1950-1951 (Box 4)
- Philippine Institute of Public Administration Project, 1952-1957